So with the concept of inheritance that we had a look at in the last video now let's just
dive in and write some actual code and you will see how do we go about inheritance in the Java
programming language. What I'll do is in the work package I'll say right click new and I'll just
create a new Java class. Let's call this as inheritance term.
All right. So this has the main method and now to demonstrate that I'll just take that idea
along only that is the idea of human and just say class human and this is how you do it in Java
you have these classes right and then I'll say for example white, green and just put in a sample
message that is humans breed. All you have to think is that how do humans breathe? You would
define that logic inside void meet a breed method and whenever you need to call it obviously
call it with an object right. Similarly what I'll do is I'll say white, eat and I'll just put in
this out I'll say inside or for now humans eat right. Let's copy this one more time. Let's say in
human for now we have three methods humans can do three things only but you know in the real world
they can do so much right. All of that would go in this class human but for now let's take this is
white work and I'll say humans this is a normal class no irritants inheritance for now but now I'll say class
and it extends from human. So what I did is on that diagram where I was drawing it for you I
showed inheritance with an arrow but in Java we use the keyword extends and the moment you do
extends the JVM the Java environment knows that this is now a subclass of this super class right.
So subclass comes on the left of the extends keyword and super class comes on the right so this
becomes the subclass this becomes a super class that is Ranjit is a super subclass of the super
class human and the moment you do this now Ranjit is not an empty blank class because it has all
of that which was in human it has breathe it has eat it has work but just inevitably out there
right and it had a choice that it can have its own particular method as well which Ranjit did not
take but there was a class as we did on the diagram I'll say schweta and also extends from
human this is again single level inheritance and schweta now has eat walk and breathe as well as
schweta took the choice and has her own particular method as well why dance what I'll do is
I'll just put in a sound and I'll say schweta can dance but not every human can that's perfectly
fine as well absolutely fine that right but see how inheritance works and the moment you try to create
an object now what I'll do at line number five I'll obviously if you call a humans breathe eat
and walk with an object of human that's that's all story now we have been doing that from
the first video but now if you do something like this I'll say Ranjit let's call it Ranjit
an object of Ranjit and I'll just say Ranjit got breathe the moment this starts to work you know
this is something special because at first Ranjit has nothing but extends human it has
everything that you that was in human that means if you can do this you can do this as well
I can say eat I can say walk and let's see if this works and works like a child with an object
of Ranjit right you're able to call the methods which were initially originally in human
that is inheritance that is how we inherit some properties through the lineage from our ancestors
from our parents grandparents and and and so on right and similarly if you do something like this
I'll say Schrader that's all the object reference variable I'll show it as well and I'll say
Schrader dot breathe and in no particular order daughter is not Ranjit Schrader dot for
example walk I just need to call breathe and walk from Schrader now let's say I don't have to call
eat right Schrader doesn't want to eat right now she wants to eat after one hour that's perfectly
fine right okay let's just requirement driven just because you call three methods from Ranjit
you do not have to necessarily call it from Schrader as well think about it right
and when you do that when this works you would know this is inheritance see first humans breathe
eat and walk from Ranjit's object and then Schrader's object humans breathe and walk as well
and now with an object of Schrader I can even call dance later on and it would tell you in
addition to Schrader being breathing walking she can also dance and she can do that really well
right so that Ranjit cannot dance I told you that is just because their siblings doesn't mean
they can access each other properties I can never do this put in the comment
doesn't work because this method is neither found in human it's not found in Ranjit it's a
unique personal method of Schrader only an object of Schrader can call dance or the subclasses of
Schrader can also call it right no right so this is a single level there's a single level
but let's say I have one more class here and I'll say for example class let's say snina
this time it extends from Schrader okay this is inheritance but this time it is multilevel
that is inside snia you would have properties of Schrader as well as of human as well as sni has
old properties see I don't have anything else here but if you do something like this let's say
it's new the the most effective way I create an object I say dance I can call because this method
was inherited from sni has parent or super class that was Schrader and that is found in sni
high as well this should work it says in sni high as well Schrader can dance so that is the basic
form of inheritance how does it work with the keyword extends right so again after this video is
done just spend some time just hold on please let me stop the timer I'm sorry the timer
ran so I was just saying that the video is done they just put in your hands dirty again
and just write some code not just based on class human but anything that comes to your mind
because as I said we are just revolved around with the classes of with the idea of classes and
objects you can just envision everything around you as classes and objects just take this idea
forward and write your own code in the next video we'll try to make it a bit more sophisticated
see what else we can do with inheritance and trust me on that we can do so much more